Jalani Kofi Williams

PhD Student, Computer Science Department, Carnegie Mellon University Gates 5007, 5000 Forbes Ave, Pittsburgh, PA 15213 jalaniw@cs.cmu.edu https://jalaniw.github.jo

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Broadly, Jalani is interested in applying techniques from probability and decision making under uncertainty to guide the design of large-scale service systems (e.g. datacenters). In the long term, he aims to create a world where all such systems are designed using a combination of theoretical insight and domain-specific data --a world where we can guarantee *by design* that a system is efficient, performant, and robust. Recently, Jalani has been focusing on understanding how the energy-saving methods being used in today's datacenters affect the fundamental characteristics of their latency performance.

related areas: applied probability, queueing theory, cloud computing, decision-making under uncertainty

EDUCATION

Carnegie Mellon University – Pittsburgh, PA

August 2018 – Ongoing Advisor: Weina Wang

6th year PhD student in the Computer Science Department.

California Institute of Technology -- Pasadena, CA

October 2012 – June 2016

B.S. Mechanical Engineering, Minor in Computer Science

AWARDS

CAARMS Poster Award, "Best Algorithm" for The M/M/k with Deterministic Setup Times, 2023

Invited Participant, Stanford MS&E Rising Stars Program, 2023

CAARMS Poster Award, "Best Theory" for Towards Understanding the M/M/k/Setup, 2022

GEM Fellowship, 2021

Gates Millennium Scholarship, 2012-2021

PUBLICATIONS

- Jalani Williams, Weina Wang, Mor Harchol-Balter. The M/M/k/Setup with deterministic setup times. *Proc. ACM SIGMETRICS Int. Conf. Measurement and Modeling of Computer Systems (SIGMETRICS)*, June 19 June 23, 2023, Orlando, FL.
- Weina Wang, Anupam Gupta, Jalani Williams. Probing to Minimize. Proc. Conf. on Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science (ITCS), January 31 - February 3, 2022, Berkeley, CA.
- Cristina Segalin, Jalani Williams, Tomomi Karigo, et al. The Mouse Action Recognition System (MARS) software pipeline for automated analysis of social behaviors in mice. *eLife*. 2021.

PRESENTATIONS

- "The M/M/k with Deterministic Setup Times," CAARMS 2023, Poster
- "The M/M/k with Deterministic Setup Times," SIGMETRICS 2023, Invited Talk
- "Setup Times in Multiserver Systems," Cornell ORIE Colloquium, Invited Talk
- "Setup Times in Multiserver Systems," Stanford MS&E Rising Stars 2023, Invited Talk
- "Understanding the M/M/k/Setup-Deterministic," Simons Institute Data-Driven Decision-making Processes Program, Poster
- "A Tight Analysis of Server Farms with Setup Times," INFORMS Annual Meeting, Invited Talk
- "Towards Understanding the M/M/k/Setup," CAARMS 2022, Poster
- "Towards Understanding the M/M/k/Setup," Stochastic Networks 2022, Poster
- "Probing To Minimize," ITCS 2022, Invited Talk
- "Stochastic Routing with Minimum Cost," SIGMETRICS 2019, Poster

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate TA, "Analytical Performance Modeling" (15-857/47-774) - Carnegie Mellon University September 2021 – December 2021

Instructors: Mor Harchol-Balter and Weina Wang

Part of a team of two TAs. Together, we were responsible for creating recitation materials, leading recitation sessions, holding regular office hours, and grading assignments and exams.

Head TA, "Probability and Computing" (15-259/260) - Carnegie Mellon University

February 2021 – May 2021

Instructors: Mor Harchol-Balter and Weina Wang

Led a team of six TAs. Together, we were responsible for creating recitation materials, leading recitation sessions, holding regular office hours, and grading assignments and exams. For an associated "Statistics and Computing" mini-course, lectured for 2 out of the 6 lectures.

UNIVERSITY SERVICE

CSD PhD Student Council, Apparel Working Group

August 2021 – (ongoing)

Part of a team responsible for creating, ordering, and distributing various department apparel (e.g. tshirts, hoodies).

Student Volunteer, CSD Introductory Course

August 2019 - September 2019

Part of a group responsible for organizing and assisting with various new student activities. Included planning research area-specific parties, participating in a student panel, and other volunteer miscellanea.